A Guide to the Secretary of the Commonwealth, Records, 1867-1929 1867-1929
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Records, 1867-1929
Library of Virginia
25299
4.95 cubic feet
Secretary of the Commonwealth
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Transferred from the Office of the Secretary of the Commonwealth, 24 March 1961.
Biographical/Historical Information
The Office of the Secretary of the Commonwealth has evolved from early colonial times when there existed a Secretary of the Colony. Thomas Nelson held the position of the first Secretary of Virginia in 1776. Early Secretaries were elected by the public. An Act of the General Assembly in 1920 changed the election to a joint vote of the General Assembly. In a 1930 Act the duties of the Secretary were redefined with the Secretary of the Commonwealth serving as the ex officio secretary of the Governor, as custodian of many official State records, and as keeper of the Greater and Lesser Seals of the Commonwealth. The office of the Secretary has gradually acquired other functions, such as: service of out-of-state civil process; appointment and regulation of notaries public; and registration and oversight of lobbyists. The Office became a gubernational appointment subsequent to a 1958 Act of the Assembly. The Secretary of the Commonwealth is under the jurisdiction of the Governor's Office.
Scope and Content Information
Arranged into the following series: Series I. Applications and recommendations for appointments to state positions, 1870-1873, 1883; Series II. Applications and recommendations for appointments as Inspector of Tobacco, 1870-1876; Series III. Applications and recommendations for appointments as local officials, 1870; Series IV. Correspondence from governors of other states, 1869-1874; Series V. Miscellaneous records, 1872-1906; Series VI. Penitentiary papers, 1867-1897; Series VII. Records of various state institutions and asylums, 1870-1897; Series VIII. Notifications of candidacy, 1900; Series IX. Miscellaneous papers of the Adjutant General, 1880-1897; Series X. Contracts and bonds for printing, 1903-1919; and Series XI. Contracts and bonds for ruling and binding, 1903-1919.
Series I. Applications and recommendations for appointments to state positions, 1870-1874, 1883. Includes applications and recommendations for various state positions, including boundary commissioner, clerkships, Geological Survey, fish inspectors, flour inspectors, lumber inspectors, provisions inspectors, Public Guard, State Board of Health, and the Board of Visitors at the University of Virginia. Arranged alphabetically.
Series II. Applications and recommendations for appointments as Inspectors of Tobacco, 1870-1876. Includes applications and recommendations for appointments in Farmville, 1874-1875; Lynchburg, 1870-1872; Petersburg, 1870-1871, 1875; Richmond, 1874-1876. Arranged alphabetically by city, and thereunder chronologically.
Series III. Applications and recommendations for appointments as local officials, 1870. Includes applications and recommendations for local officials in various Virginia counties and cities, including constables, councilmen, justices of the peace, magistrates and trustees. Arranged alphabetically by locality.
Series IV. Correspondence from governors of other states, 1869-1874. Includes correspondence to Virginia Governors Gilbert C. Walker and James L. Kemper from various governors of other states regarding a variety of topics. Arranged chronologically.
Series V. Miscellaneous records, 1872-1906. This series includes the following: Annual reports of the Board of Visitors at the University of Virginia, 1872-1873; Bond of the Secretary of the Commonwealth, 1906; Certificate of organization for the Seafood Investment Company, 1892; Contract for metal fixtures and furniture for the Office of the Secretary of the Commonwealth, 1906; Miscellaneous correspondence, 1873, 1877, 1897, 1899; Leases for state property, 1866, 1879 (Public Warehouse and Armory); List of books delivered to the University of Virginia, 1896; List of textbook regulations in other states, c. 1877; Memorial of the Pamunkey Tribe, 1877; Papers related to the Mutual Endowment Association of Virginia, c. 1880; Petition to Governor Kemper regarding assistance to former Governor Letcher during his illness, c. 1874-1878; Reports of visitors to Mt. Vernon, 1896; Reports of debt from other states, 1873; State of the Public Debt of the United States, 1871; Various papers from the Office of the Secretary of the Commonwealth, n.d.; West Virginia Act regarding the taking of fish from the Potomac River, 1897. Arranged alphabetically.
Series VI. Penitentiary papers, 1867-1897. Includes: Applications and recommendations for the positions of director, board of directors, clerk of the board of directors, superintendent, and commissioner of revenue at the Virginia State Penitentiary, 1870, 1872 and 1874; Applications and recommendations for the position of physician, 1869-1870 and 1873-1874; Monthly reports of prisoners received, discharged, pardoned, died, escaped, etc., 1894-1897; Quarterly financial and surgeon reports, 1894-1897. Financial reports include information on receipts, deposits and disbursements and surgeons reports include information on the number of patients excused from work, the number of patients treated at the hospital and their ailments, and the number of deaths at the prison hospital; Miscellaneous financial reports, 1871-1874; Quarterly reports of the Board of Directors, 1872-1874, which include statements on manufacturing operations, receipts and expenditures, and written reports; Special reports, 1869 and 1872, including a report regarding hauling rock from Capitol Square, 1869, a report of the Commission appointed by Special Order 250, 1869, and a report made with regard to one of the Guard of convicts and his dereliction of duty, 1872; Correspondence and contracts regarding convict labor, 1867-1873; Correspondence regarding escapees, fugitives and rewards, 1869-1871; and Miscellaneous papers, 1867-1877, most of which concern individual convicts, prison conditions and pay, and also includes National Prison Association circulars.
Series VII. Records of various state institutions and asylums, 1870-1897. This series includes correspondence, recommendations and reports for the following state institutions and asylums: Central Lunatic Asylum, 1870-1874; Mount Vernon, 1896; the "New" Lunatic Asylum, 1872-1874; Southwestern State Hospital, 1894-1897; Virginia Institution for the Education of the Deaf, Dumb and Blind, 1896-1897; and the Western Lunatic Asylum, 1869-1875. Arranged alphabetically.
Series VIII. Notifications of candidacy, 1900. These letters consist of official notices of candidacy to the Secretary of the Commonwealth for Congressional offices and electors for President and Vice- President for 1900. These notices were required by law and requested that the candidate's name be placed on the official ballot.
Series IX. Miscellaneous papers of the Adjutant General, 1880-1897. These papers include mostly incoming correspondence and receipts for supplies for the years 1880-1888; 1895; and 1897. Arranged chronologically.
Series X. Contracts and bonds for printing, 1903-1919. Includes ontracts and bonds for the printing of state government publications. Also includes a petition for a contract and transcripts of the ensuing hearing (1907). Arranged chronologically.
Series XI. Contracts and bonds for ruling and binding, 1903-1919. Includes contracts and bonds for the ruling and binding of state government publications. Arranged chronologically.
Contents List
- Series I: Applications and recommendations for appointments to state positions, 1873-1874; 1883
  Arranged alphabetically by position.
  - Boundary Commissioners, 1870 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Boundary Commissioners, 1872 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Boundary Commissioners, 1873 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Clerkship in the Executive Dept., 1870 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Clerkship in the Executive Dept., 1871 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Clerkship in the Executive Dept., 1872 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Coroner - Richmond, 1872 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Geological Survey, 1883 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Inspector of Fish - Alexandria, 1870 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Inspector of Fish - Alexandria, 1872 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Inspector of Fish - Alexandria, 1874 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Inspector of Fish - Fredericksburg, 1874 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Inspector of Fish - Norfolk, 1874 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Inspector of Fish - Petersburg, 1870 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Inspector of Fish - Petersburg, 1874 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Inspector of Fish - Richmond, 1870 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Inspector of Flour - Chesterfield, 1871 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Inspector of Flour - Portsmouth, 1871 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Inspector of Lumber - Norfolk, 1874 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Inspector of Lumber - Portsmouth, 1874 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Inspector of Provisions - Norfolk, 1870 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Inspector of Provisions - Richmond, 1871 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Public Guard, 1870 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Public Guard, 1871 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - State Board of Health, 1870 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - University of Virginia - Board of Visitors, 1872 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - University of Virginia - Board of Visitors, 1873 (Box 1, Folder 27)
- Series II: Applications and recommendations for appointments as Inspector of Tobacco, 1870-1876
  Arranged alphabetically by locality.
  - Inspector of Tobacco - Farmville, 1874 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Inspector of Tobacco - Farmville, 1875 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Inspector of Tobacco - Lynchburg, 1870 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Inspector of Tobacco - Lynchburg, 1871 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Inspector of Tobacco - Lynchburg, 1872 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Inspector of Tobacco - Petersburg, 1870 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Inspector of Tobacco - Petersburg, 1871 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Inspector of Tobacco - Petersburg, 1875 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Inspector of Tobacco - Richmond, 1874 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Inspector of Tobacco - Richmond, 1875 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Inspector of Tobacco - Richmond, 1876 (Box 2, Folder 11)
- Series III: Applications and recommendations for appointments as local officials, 1870
  - Accomack County, 1870 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Amelia County, 1870 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Augusta County, 1870 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Bedford County, 1870 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Botetourt County, 1870 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Brunswick County, 1870 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Buckingham County, 1870 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Chesterfield County, 1870 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Culpeper County, 1870 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - King William County, 1870 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Loudoun County, 1870 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Louisa County, 1870 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Nansemond County, 1870 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - New Kent County, 1870 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Norfolk County, 1870 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Northumberland County, 1870 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Orange County, 1870 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Pittsylvania County, 1870 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Prince Edward County, 1870 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Prince William County, 1870 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Richmond County, 1870 (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Roanoke County, 1870 (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Rockingham County, 1870 (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Russell County, 1870 (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Scott County, 1870 (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - Shenandoah County, 1870 (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - Smyth County, 1870 (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - Stafford County, 1870 (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - Surry County, 1870 (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - Sussex County, 1870 (Box 3, Folder 30)
  - Tazewell County, 1870 (Box 3, Folder 31)
  - Warren County, 1870 (Box 3, Folder 32)
  - Washington County, 1870 (Box 3, Folder 33)
  - Westmoreland County, 1870 (Box 3, Folder 34)
  - Wythe County, 1870 (Box 3, Folder 35)
  - Abingdon, 1870 (Box 3, Folder 36)
  - Alexandra, 1870 (Box 3, Folder 37)
  - Charlottesville, 1870 (Box 3, Folder 38)
  - Danville, 1870 (Box 3, Folder 39)
  - Harrisonburg, 1870 (Box 3, Folder 40)
  - Lynchburg, 1870 (Box 3, Folder 41)
  - Manchester, 1870 (Box 3, Folder 42)
  - Norfolk, 1870 (Box 3, Folder 43)
  - Petersburg, 1870 (Box 3, Folder 44)
  - Portsmouth, 1870 (Box 3, Folder 45)
  - Richmond, 1870 (Box 3, Folder 46)
  - Scottsville, 1870 (Box 3, Folder 47)
  - Staunton, 1870 (Box 3, Folder 48)
  - Suffolk, 1870 (Box 3, Folder 49)
  - Warrenton, 1870 (Box 3, Folder 50)
  - Winchester, 1870 (Box 3, Folder 51)
- Series IV: Correspondence from governors of other states, 1869-1874
  Arranged chronologically.
  - Correspondence, 1869 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, 1870 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, 1871 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, 1872 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, 1873 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, 1874 (Box 4, Folder 6)
- Series V: Miscellaneous records, 1872-1906
  Arranged alphabetically.
  - Annual reports of the Board of Visitors at the University of Virginia, 1872-1873 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Bond of the Secretary of the Commonwealth, 1906 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Certificate of organization for the Seafood Investment Company, 1892 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Contract for Metal Fixtures and Furniture for the Office of the Secretary of the Commonwealth, 1906 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence of the Secretary of the Commonwealth, 1873; 1877; 1897; 1899 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Leases for state property, 1866; 1879 (Public Warehouse and Armory) (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - List of books delivered to the University of Virginia Library, 1896 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - List of textbook regulations in other states, c. 1877 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Memorial of the Pamunkey Tribe, 1877 (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Papers related to the Mutual Endowment Association of Virginia, c. 1880 (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Petition to Governor Kemper regarding assistance to former Governor Letcher during his illness, c. 1874-1878 (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Report of visitors to Mount Vernon, 1896 (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - Reports on debt from other states (A-K), 1873 (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - Reports on debt from other states (M-N), 1873 (Box 4, Folder 20)
  - Reports on debt from other states (O-W), 1873 (Box 4, Folder 21)
  - Statement of the Public Debt of the United States, 1871 (Box 4, Folder 22)
  - Various papers from the Office of the Secretary of the Commonwealth, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 23)
  - West Virginia Act regarding the taking of fish from the Potomac River, 1897 (Box 4, Folder 24)
  - Notary public commission for Frederick Pilcher, 1903 (Box 4, Folder 25)
- Series VI: Penitentiary papers, 1867-1897
  - Applications and recommendations for positions at the Virginia State Penitentiary, 1870; 1872; 1874 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Applications and recommendations for Penitentiary physician, 1869-1870 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Applications and recommendations for Penitentiary physician, 1873-1874 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Monthly reports of prisoners received, discharged, pardoned, died, escaped, etc., 1894 Jan-Jul and Sep-Dec (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Monthly reports of prisoners received, discharged, pardoned, died, escaped, etc., 1895 Jan-May and Jul-Dec (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Monthly reports of prisoners received, discharged, pardoned, died, escaped, etc., 1896 Jan-Dec (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Monthly reports of prisoners received, discharged, pardoned, died, escaped, etc., 1897 Feb-Nov (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Miscellaneous financial reports, 1871-1872; 1874 Jun (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Quarterly financial and surgeon reports, 1894-1897 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Quarterly reports of the Board of Directors, 1872-1874 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Special reports, 1869; 1872 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Convict labor: Correspondence and contracts, 1867-1868 (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Convict labor: Correspondence and contracts, 1870 (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Convict labor: Correspondence and contracts, 1871 (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - Convict labor: Correspondence and contracts, 1872 (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - Convict labor: Correspondence and contracts, 1873 (Box 5, Folder 16)
  - Convict labor: Correspondence and contracts, 1874 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Convict labor: Correspondence and contracts, 1875 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Convict labor: Correspondence and contracts, 1877 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Convict labor: Correspondence and contracts, 1878 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Convict labor: Correspondence and contracts, 1879 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Convict labor: Correspondence and contracts, 1880 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Convict labor: Correspondence and contracts, 1881 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Convict labor: Correspondence and contracts, 1882 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Convict labor: Correspondence and contracts, 1883 (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Convict labor: Correspondence and contracts, 1885 (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - Convict labor: Correspondence and contracts, 1890 (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - Convict labor: Correspondence and contracts, 1891 (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - Escapees, fugitives and rewards: Correpsondence, 1869-1871 (Box 6, Folder 13)
  - Miscellaneous papers, 1867-1871 (Box 6, Folder 14)
  - Miscellaneous papers, 1872 (Box 6, Folder 15)
  - Miscellaneous papers, 1873-1877 (Box 6, Folder 16)
- Series VII: Records of various state institutions and asylums, 1870-1897
  Arranged alphabetically by institution.
  - Central Lunatic Asylum, 1870-1874 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - New Lunatic Asylum, 1872-1874 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Southwestern State Hospital, 1894-1897 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Virginia Institution for the Education of the Deaf, Dumb and Blind, 1896-1897 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Western Lunatic Asylum, 1869-1871 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Western Lunatic Asylum, 1872 (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Western Lunatic Asylum, 1873 (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Western Lunatic Asylum, 1874 (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - Western Lunatic Asylum, 1875 (Box 7, Folder 9)
- Series VIII: Notifications of Candidacy, 1900
  - Notification, 1900 (Box 7, Folder 10)
- Series IX: Miscellaneous papers of the Adjutant General, 1880-1897
  - Miscellaneous papers, 1880-1888 (Box 7, Folder 11)
  - Miscellaneous papers, 1895; 1897 (Box 7, Folder 12)
  - Miscellaneous papers, n.d. (Box 7, Folder 13)
- Series X: Contracts and bonds for printing, 1903-1919
  - Contracts and bonds, 1903-1904 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Contracts and bonds, 1904-1905 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Contracts and bonds, 1906-1907 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Contracts and bonds, 1907-1908 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Contracts and bonds, 1908-1909 (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Contracts and bonds, 1909-1910 (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - Contracts and bonds, 1910-1911 (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - Contracts and bonds, 1911-1912 (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - Contracts and bonds, 1912-1913 (Box 8, Folder 9)
  - Contracts and bonds, 1913-1914 (Box 8, Folder 10)
  - Contracts and bonds, 1915-1916 (Box 8, Folder 11)
  - Contracts and bonds, 1918-1919 (Box 8, Folder 12)
  - Petition for printing contract, 1907 (Box 8, Folder 13)
- Series XI: Contracts and bonds for ruling and binding, 1903-1919
  - Contracts and bonds, 1903-1904 (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Contracts and bonds, 1904-1905 (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Contracts and bonds, 1905-1906 (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - Contracts and bonds, 1907-1908 (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - Contracts and bonds, 1908-1909 (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - Contracts and bonds, 1909-1910 (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - Contracts and bonds, 1910-1911 (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - Contracts and bonds, 1911-1912 (Box 9, Folder 8)
  - Contracts and bonds, 1912-1913 (Box 9, Folder 9)
  - Contracts and bonds, 1913-1914 (Box 9, Folder 10)
  - Contracts and bonds, 1915-1916 (Box 9, Folder 11)
  - Contracts and bonds, 1916-1917 (Box 9, Folder 12)
  - Contracts and bonds, 1918-1919 (Box 9, Folder 13)